<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<DialogueFile npc="BrendylWheyfoot">

  <Dialogue id="greeting">
    <NPCText>
      <![CDATA[
      <BASEFONT COLOR='#e6e2c2'>
      A stooped man with curd-stained robes eyes you warily while rearranging rounds of cheese in mismatched baskets.<br>
      <i>"You there—yes, you look like someone who values fine dairy and a faint hint of mystery."</i><br><br>
      He clutches a cheese wheel like a holy relic.<br>
      <b>"I'm Brendyl Wheyfoot, and I’m in dire need of aid. Have you ever met a true Cheese Maker? No? Well then. This may be your destiny."</b>
      </BASEFONT>
    ]]>
    </NPCText>
    <Option text="A Cheese Maker? That’s... oddly specific." next="explain"/>
    <Option text="What sort of aid are you looking for?" next="questIntro"/>
    <Option text="I’m lactose intolerant. Goodbye." action="Close"/>
  </Dialogue>

  <Dialogue id="explain">
    <NPCText>
      <![CDATA[
      <BASEFONT COLOR='#e6e2c2'>
      “He was once the Crown’s Royal Curdmaster—Theodor Curdswain. Said to have created a blue-veined wedge so potent it cured lycanthropy. But after Lord British vanished, Theodor disappeared too.”<br>
      Brendyl sighs, eyes watering.<br>
      “Last I heard, he’d retreated to the caves north of Wind, mumbling about soul cultures and sacred molds. I fear for him.”
      </BASEFONT>
    ]]>
    </NPCText>
    <Option text="You want me to find him?" next="questIntro"/>
    <Option text="That sounds like a you-problem." action="Close"/>
  </Dialogue>

  <Dialogue id="questIntro">
    <NPCText>
      <![CDATA[
      <BASEFONT COLOR='#e6e2c2'>
      Brendyl offers a tightly wrapped parchment.<br>
      “I’ve prepared a delivery scroll, bound by goatgut twine and dairy ink. You need only find Theodor Curdswain—the man bearing the trait of <b>Cheese Maker</b>—and hand him this message.”<br><br>
      “Do this, and the Artisan’s Circle of Frostmere will honor you with reputation... and perhaps a wheel of something pungent and delightful.”
      </BASEFONT>
    ]]>
    </NPCText>
    <Option text="I’ll find this Cheese Maker for you."
            action="GiveItem:FactionDeliveryQuestScroll(Cheese Maker,Frostmere,250)"
            condition="!HasItem:FactionDeliveryQuestScroll"
            next="accept"/>
    <Option text="Any clues to where he is now?" next="clues"/>
    <Option text="I must decline. Cheese is not my path." action="Close"/>
  </Dialogue>

  <Dialogue id="clues">
    <NPCText>
      <![CDATA[
      Brendyl sniffs the air as if following a scent.<br>
      “I once tracked his trail to a frozen waterfall near Wind. There were odd holes in the snow—round and faintly fragrant. His signs. But beware—Theodor was never the same after he invented the Lamenting Brie.”<br>
      He stares into the distance.<br>
      “You’ll know him by the smell. Like regret, aged 20 years.”
      ]]>
    </NPCText>
    <Option text="I'll deliver your scroll to Theodor."
            action="GiveItem:FactionDeliveryQuestScroll(Cheese Maker,Frostmere,250)"
            condition="!HasItem:FactionDeliveryQuestScroll"
            next="accept"/>
    <Option text="On second thought, this sounds insane." action="Close"/>
  </Dialogue>

  <Dialogue id="accept">
    <NPCText>
      <![CDATA[
      Brendyl nods solemnly.<br>
      “Blessings of the Buttered Saint be upon you. Find Theodor. Deliver the scroll. Let him know his cheeses are missed... and his return awaited.”<br><br>
      He bows, pressing the scroll into your hands.
      ]]>
    </NPCText>
    <Option text="I’ll find him. Farewell, Wheyfoot." action="Close"/>
  </Dialogue>

</DialogueFile>
