<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<DialogueFile npc="LadySeraphineAshveil">

  <Dialogue id="greeting">
    <NPCText>
      <![CDATA[
      <BASEFONT COLOR='#db3041'>
      A striking woman stands before you, clad in crimson and midnight, her eyes alight with mischief and danger. Silver hair tumbles from beneath a jeweled tricorne.<BR><BR>
      She offers a crooked smile.<BR>
      "Welcome to Sunreach, darling. Here, gold speaks, secrets drown, and loyalty is ever negotiable. I am Lady Seraphine Ashveil—pirate, duchess, and the true wind behind these sails.<BR><BR>
      What brings you to my city? Business, pleasure... or a taste of forbidden waters?"
      </BASEFONT>
      ]]>
    </NPCText>
    <Option text="I'm looking for work. Anything that pays well?" next="workIntro"/>
    <Option text="Who are you, exactly?" next="backstory"/>
    <Option text="Tell me about the Ashveil Corsairs." next="corsairLore"/>
    <Option text="What do you know of Minax's agents?" next="minaxIntro"/>
	<Option text="I want to know more about *you*, Seraphine." next="seraphineIntro"/>
    <Option text="Just passing through." next="dismiss"/>
  </Dialogue>

  <!-- Backstory branch -->
  <Dialogue id="backstory">
    <NPCText>
      <![CDATA[
      She laughs, rich and smoky.<BR>
      "Oh, my reputation hasn't reached your ears? I command the Ashveil Corsairs—every ship, shadow, and secret that moves through Sunreach owes me a cut. Some call me a pirate queen, others a snake in silk. I say I simply keep the true order of things.<BR>
      Darius Veynar and his merchant council think they rule the city. But without my ships and my silence, their precious gold would feed the sharks."
      ]]>
    </NPCText>
    <Option text="What do you want from me?" next="workIntro"/>
    <Option text="What’s your connection to Darius Veynar?" next="darius"/>
    <Option text="Enough about you—any work?" next="workIntro"/>
  </Dialogue>

  <Dialogue id="darius">
    <NPCText>
      <![CDATA[
      Her eyes flash.<BR>
      "Darius and I have... an arrangement. He keeps the council looking the other way, and I ensure the right ships reach the right hands. But alliances shift like tides. Should he forget who truly owns these waters, well—he knows what secrets might wash ashore."
      ]]>
    </NPCText>
    <Option text="You’re not afraid of him?" next="workIntro"/>
    <Option text="Let’s talk business, then." next="workIntro"/>
  </Dialogue>

  <Dialogue id="corsairLore">
    <NPCText>
      <![CDATA[
      "The Ashveil Corsairs are more than cutthroats and smugglers—we’re the lifeblood of Sunreach’s trade, darling. Every ship pays our 'tax,' be it silks or secrets. Cross us, and you’ll find the sharks less merciless.<BR>
      I keep my crew loyal—gold, favor, fear... and a touch of forbidden magic for those who step out of line."
      ]]>
    </NPCText>
    <Option text="Is that magic from Minax?" next="minaxIntro"/>
    <Option text="How can I join your crew?" next="workIntro"/>
    <Option text="Let’s talk business." next="workIntro"/>
  </Dialogue>

  <Dialogue id="minaxIntro">
    <NPCText>
      <![CDATA[
      Her tone turns icy.<BR>
      "Minax is a storm most try to outrun, but I prefer to sail through it—if I must. Some say I've made pacts with her cultists for certain... advantages. Perhaps I have. In Sunreach, only fools pick one side.<BR>
      But beware—her gifts come with hooks. Cross her, and you may drown in more than just the tide."
      ]]>
    </NPCText>
    <Option text="Are you offering me work or warning?" next="workIntro"/>
    <Option text="What are Minax’s cultists doing here?" next="cultists"/>
    <Option text="Maybe I’m in over my head..." next="dismiss"/>
  </Dialogue>

  <Dialogue id="cultists">
    <NPCText>
      <![CDATA[
      She lowers her voice.<BR>
      "They skulk beneath Sunreach—blood cults, smugglers, and shadow priests. Some serve Minax directly, others simply ride her chaos for profit. I keep the worst in check, for a price. If you’re brave—or foolish—enough, I may have a job rooting out a traitor who serves both my rivals and Minax."
      ]]>
    </NPCText>
    <Option text="I can handle myself. Tell me more." next="workIntro"/>
    <Option text="I’m not sure I want to get involved..." next="dismiss"/>
  </Dialogue>

  <Dialogue id="dismiss">
    <NPCText>
      <![CDATA[
      "A wise traveler never lingers in Sunreach without a purpose. If your coin or courage increases, you know where to find me."
      ]]>
    </NPCText>
    <Option text="On second thought, got any work?" next="workIntro"/>
    <Option text="Farewell." action="Close"/>
  </Dialogue>

  <!-- Quest Introduction -->
  <Dialogue id="workIntro">
    <NPCText>
      <![CDATA[
      <BASEFONT COLOR='#db3041'>
      Seraphine leans in, voice a velvet whisper.<BR><BR>
      "I have a task—dangerous, but lucrative. One of my lieutenants, Captain Rhogar Blackwake, suspects a traitor among our ranks: someone feeding information to the council *and* Minax’s cultists.<BR>
      I need an outsider—someone the crew won’t suspect—to sniff out the rat.<BR><BR>
      Find out who’s betraying us, plant this ‘Coin of the False Tide’ among their belongings as proof, and report back. Succeed, and I’ll see you rewarded in coin, favor... and perhaps a little forbidden power."
      </BASEFONT>
      ]]>
    </NPCText>
    <Option text="Give me the Coin. I'll find your traitor."
            action="GiveItem:FactionQuestItem(CoinOfTheFalseTide,Sunreach,1)"
            condition="!HasItem:CoinOfTheFalseTide"
            next="acceptQuest"/>
    <Option text="Who are my suspects?" next="suspects"/>
    <Option text="What if I’m caught?" next="risk"/>
    <Option text="What’s in it for me?" next="reward"/>
    <Option text="Maybe this isn’t for me." action="Close"/>
  </Dialogue>

  <!-- Accept Quest -->
  <Dialogue id="acceptQuest">
    <NPCText>
      <![CDATA[
      Seraphine slips you a coin etched with strange runes.<BR>
      "Plant this coin in the traitor’s chest or satchel—then return with their name. Captain Rhogar or Aria Silverhand can point you toward likely suspects. And beware: in Sunreach, eyes and daggers are everywhere.<BR><BR>
      Betray me, and the sea’s mercy will be greater than mine."
      ]]>
    </NPCText>
    <Option text="Understood. I’ll return with proof." action="Close"/>
  </Dialogue>

  <!-- Suspects branch -->
  <Dialogue id="suspects">
    <NPCText>
      <![CDATA[
      "Rhogar’s got his doubts about a dock foreman named Scully, a quartermaster called Mara Fen, and even Aria Silverhand herself. The cultists are clever, and so are my rivals. Talk to them all, trust none."
      ]]>
    </NPCText>
    <Option text="I’m ready to begin." 
            action="GiveItem:FactionQuestItem(CoinOfTheFalseTide,Sunreach,1)"
            condition="!HasItem:CoinOfTheFalseTide"
            next="acceptQuest"/>
    <Option text="What should I watch for?" next="risk"/>
    <Option text="On second thought, never mind." action="Close"/>
  </Dialogue>

  <!-- Risk branch -->
  <Dialogue id="risk">
    <NPCText>
      <![CDATA[
      Seraphine grins wolfishly.<BR>
      "If you’re caught, you’re on your own. My name will not save you, and the traitor may be as deadly as any cultist. But if you succeed, you’ll have proven your worth—to me, and to every power in Sunreach."
      ]]>
    </NPCText>
    <Option text="Worth the risk. I’ll do it."
            action="GiveItem:FactionQuestItem(CoinOfTheFalseTide,Sunreach,1)"
            condition="!HasItem:CoinOfTheFalseTide"
            next="acceptQuest"/>
    <Option text="I’ll reconsider." action="Close"/>
  </Dialogue>

  <!-- Reward branch -->
  <Dialogue id="reward">
    <NPCText>
      <![CDATA[
      "Gold, of course—enough to buy silence or a swift ship. If you please me, perhaps a pirate’s mark of favor: protection in my waters and a taste of the magic Minax thought only she could grant. Power has many forms, darling."
      ]]>
    </NPCText>
    <Option text="The reward is worth it. I’m in."
            action="GiveItem:FactionQuestItem(CoinOfTheFalseTide,Sunreach,1)"
            condition="!HasItem:CoinOfTheFalseTide"
            next="acceptQuest"/>
    <Option text="No reward is worth my head. Goodbye." action="Close"/>
  </Dialogue>

<Dialogue id="seraphineIntro">
  <NPCText>
    <![CDATA[
    Seraphine's smile widens just slightly, as if amused by your curiosity.<BR><BR>
    "Bold. Most ask about my riches or my blades—not the woman behind them. Very well... ask, and I may indulge you. But mind your questions. A pirate’s past can be sharp-edged."
    ]]>
  </NPCText>
  <Option text="Where did you grow up?" next="origin"/>
  <Option text="Why piracy? You could rule a noble court." next="nobility"/>
  <Option text="What do you desire most?" next="desire"/>
  <Option text="You seem drawn to power *and* danger. Why?" next="power"/>
  <Option text="This was a mistake." action="SendMessage:Seraphine laughs softly, as if you’ve proven her point."/>
  <Option text="Tell me more about Sunreach." next="sunreachLore"/>
</Dialogue>

<Dialogue id="origin">
  <NPCText>
    <![CDATA[
    "I was born on a Qasarian trading ship in the Crescent Gulf—my mother, a merchant’s daughter; my father, her hired sword and soon her lover. We made port in Nujel’m once, but I hated its velvet cages.<BR><BR>
    I found freedom at sea, but I learned early: no one gives you power—you seize it, or die begging for it."
    ]]>
  </NPCText>
  <Option text="Sounds like you learned to survive young." next="nobility"/>
  <Option text="So your pirate blood runs deep." next="power"/>
</Dialogue>

<Dialogue id="nobility">
  <NPCText>
    <![CDATA[
    She chuckles darkly.<BR><BR>
    "Nobility? Please. I’ve dined with lords who poison rivals with a smile and kiss the boot of their richer peer. A noble title means little without steel or secrets.<BR>
    My corsairs respect fear, loyalty, and freedom—not bloodlines."
    ]]>
  </NPCText>
  <Option text="Still, you command loyalty. That’s power." next="power"/>
  <Option text="So, what drives you now?" next="desire"/>
</Dialogue>

<Dialogue id="desire">
  <NPCText>
    <![CDATA[
    Seraphine leans in, voice lowered.<BR><BR>
    "Desire? A future where Sunreach bows to no crown, no cult. A place ruled by its clever, not its cruel.<BR>
    But between us? I desire leverage. Over Darius. Over Minax. Over fate itself."
    ]]>
  </NPCText>
  <Option text="Leverage? That’s... ambitious." next="leverage"/>
  <Option text="And would you use that leverage to help others?" condition="KarmaAtLeast:0" next="empathy"/>
  <Option text="You crave power. That much is clear." condition="KarmaBelow:0" next="ruthless"/>
</Dialogue>

<Dialogue id="leverage">
  <NPCText>
    <![CDATA[
    "Information. Secrets. The right whisper in the wrong ear. That’s how you survive storms, love. Even Minax fears what she doesn’t control.<BR>
    One day, she may find she doesn’t control *me*."
    ]]>
  </NPCText>
  <Option text="You walk a dangerous line." next="power"/>
</Dialogue>

<Dialogue id="empathy">
  <NPCText>
    <![CDATA[
    She pauses, genuinely surprised.<BR><BR>
    "You think me kind? Hah. I protect what’s mine—but I admit… I once spared a village Minax planned to torch. Had no profit in it, but their children reminded me of my sister."<BR>
    She shakes her head. "Dead now, of course. Burned when the cultists took the Gulf."
    ]]>
  </NPCText>
  <Option text="I’m sorry. You carry that flame well." action="AddStat:Str,5,120" next="back"/>
</Dialogue>

<Dialogue id="ruthless">
  <NPCText>
    <![CDATA[
    She narrows her eyes slightly.<BR><BR>
    "You see clearly. Yes, I crave it. Because I’ve seen what happens to the powerless. I’d burn a hundred ships to protect the few who matter."<BR>
    She offers a crooked smile. "You might survive in my world yet."
    ]]>
  </NPCText>
  <Option text="I survive wherever I go." action="AddSkill:Stealth,10,60" next="back"/>
</Dialogue>

<Dialogue id="power">
  <NPCText>
    <![CDATA[
    "Power is choice. It’s walking into a council chamber and knowing every man there owes you—coin, shame, or blood. It’s sailing toward Minax’s dark tide and daring it to break on *you*."<BR>
    She flicks a silver coin toward you—it disappears midair.<BR>
    "But true power? It's hiding that strength until the moment it matters most."
    ]]>
  </NPCText>
  <Option text="You are more than a pirate." action="AddSkill:Snooping,10,90" next="back"/>
  <Option text="That kind of power… I want it too." next="ambition"/>
</Dialogue>

<Dialogue id="ambition">
  <NPCText>
    <![CDATA[
    Her eyes glitter.<BR><BR>
    "Do you now? Then prove it. Aid me in rooting out the traitor among my Corsairs. Loyalty, after all, is just another kind of currency."<BR>
    She offers her hand.<BR>
    "Shall we test your ambition, darling?"
    ]]>
  </NPCText>
  <Option text="Give me the Coin. I’m ready to begin." 
          action="GiveItem:FactionQuestItem(CoinOfTheFalseTide,Sunreach,1)" 
          condition="!HasItem:CoinOfTheFalseTide" 
          next="acceptQuest"/>
  <Option text="Not yet. But soon." action="SendMessage:Seraphine watches you leave, amused."/>
</Dialogue>

<Dialogue id="sunreachLore">
  <NPCText>
    <![CDATA[
    "Sunreach was born of trade and betrayal. We’re the throat of the desert’s wealth, the dagger at Britannia’s ribs. Each merchant prince thinks they rule it—Darius most of all.<BR>
    But Sunreach belongs to no one. Not even me. Not yet."
    ]]>
  </NPCText>
  <Option text="You intend to change that?" next="ambition"/>
  <Option text="You sound like you *love* this city." next="cityLove"/>
</Dialogue>

<Dialogue id="cityLove">
  <NPCText>
    <![CDATA[
    She smiles—not cruelly, but almost sadly.<BR><BR>
    "I do. The chaos, the stories, the sea fog rolling in at dawn. If it falls, it won’t be to fire or Minax—it’ll be from rot within.<BR>
    I’d rather torch the harbor than let that happen."
    ]]>
  </NPCText>
  <Option text="Then let’s protect it." next="ambition"/>
  <Option text="Maybe Sunreach needs a better ruler." condition="FameAtLeast:5000" action="SendMessage:Seraphine gives you a long, thoughtful look…"/>
</Dialogue>

<Dialogue id="back">
  <NPCText>
    <![CDATA[
    Seraphine’s gaze lingers on you, a spark of interest behind her smirk.<BR>
    "You surprise me, stranger. Perhaps you're more than just another tide-washed traveler."
    ]]>
  </NPCText>
  <Option text="Let’s speak of work again." next="workIntro"/>
  <Option text="Farewell, Duchess." action="Close"/>
</Dialogue>


</DialogueFile>
